# YANAN WU

+1 (607) 372-0368 | yxw190021@utdallas.edu

gisynw.com | linkedin.com/in/giswu | github.com/gisynw | ywu120766.medium.com/

#### **SUMMARY**

PhD Student in the Geospatial Information Sciences Department at the University of Texas at Dallas. 2 years of teaching experience as an instructor, guiding students to achieve success in learning Geographic Information Science (GIScience) and statistics. Proven problem-solving, relationship-building, and negotiation through academic and research experience as a Teaching Assistant and a Research Assistant. Excellent verbal and written communication skills evident by extensive conferences and awards.

## **EDUCATION**

## **Doctor of Philosophy in Geospatial Information Sciences**

May 2024

The University of Texas at Dallas

Master of Arts in Geography

May 2019

**Binghamton University** 

### Bachelor of Science in Resource Environment and Urban-Rural Planning Management

May 2016

Xi'an University of Science and Technology, China

### **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE**

## Modeling of emergency incidents with GPS trajectory data using machine learning

July 2022 - Present

- · Led the development, training, and testing of machine learning algorithms to predict emergency dispatch
- Established interactive web maps to efficiently display GPS trajectories using ArcGIS for JavaScript and Python
- Delivered 20+ presentations, received 10 travel awards and scholarships, and gained 7 awards in talk competitions

### An Integrated Connected Vehicle and Computing Platform for Public Safety Applications

July 2019 - July 2020

- Leveraged Fourier Transformation, A-Priori Algorithm to analyze traffic accidents in Dallas
- Provided quarterly reports to supervisor, published papers and conference proceedings
- Initiated <u>Medium</u> blog posts on machine learning, Web-GIS development, and data processing using R, promoting writing skills and engaging in the online community
- Created and maintained repositories to store, track, and share codes on GitHub

## Instructor/Lecturer - Principles of Geospatial Information Sciences

May 2022- May 2023

- Gave lectures and guided students to learn in GIS through class discussions in a traditional or online classroom
- Contributed to the course material on principles of mapping, charting, and data visualization in ArcGIS Pro
- Strengthened student proficiency in Esri prodiucts, elevating geospatial data analysis skills
- Received excellent feedback from students and peer reviews, available on my personal website

## Instructor/Lecturer - Methods of Quantitative Analysis in the Social and Policy Science

May 2021 - May 2022

• Instructed and facilitated discussions with 50 students on fundamental statistical concepts and methods, including statistics, probabilities, sampling, hypothesis tests, and regression

## Integration of Earth Observation and in Situ Data for Analyzing Lake Level Changes

May 2017 - May 2019

Analyzed and interpreted global remote sensing images and GRACE data using ArcGIS Pro

## **PUBLICATIONS**

**Wu, Y.**, Yang, Y., & Yuan, M. (2023). Location analytics of routine occurrences (LARO) to identify locations with regularly occurring events with a case study on traffic accidents. *Information* (Under review)

**Wu, Y.**, Yang, Y., & Yuan, M. (2023). Understanding the role of geographical environments in emergency dispatches with GPS trajectories. *Abstracts of the ICA*, 6, 276.

**Wu, Y.**, & Yuan, M. (2021). Where and why there: location analytics of routine occurrences (LARO) with a case study on traffic accidents. *Abstracts of the ICA*, 3, 318.

### **CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS**

**Wu, Y.**, Yang, Y., Yuan, M. Analyze emergency-vehicle dispatches in Dallas, Texas, USA, In AutoCarto 2022 Proceedings.

Yang, Y., Wu, Y., Yuan, M. Quantifying the impacts of social infrastructure on human networks, In AutoCarto 2022 Proceedings.

### **AWARDS**

2023	Second Place in	Graduate P	aper Com	petition,	<b>SWAAG</b>	conference

- 2023 International Cartographic Association Scholarship
- 2023 Travel award from USNC for ICA with NSF funding to attend the ICC2023
- 2023 Betty & Gifford Johnson Travel Award, UTD
- 2022 Graduate student participants of the Grad WINGS Workshop, UCGIS
- 2022 International Cartographic Association Scholarship
- 2022 Second Place, Student Lightning Talk Award, UCGIS Symposium
- 2022 Third Place in GIS Day 2022 Awarded by Geospatial Information Sciences Program, UTD
- 2022 Travel award from UCGIS to attend the UCGIS Symposium
- 2022 The University of Texas at Dallas 2022 Three Minute Thesis (3MT) Competition, Finalist
- 2022 Honorable mentions, GI Science & Systems Student Honors Paper Competition session, AAG
- 2021 International Cartographic Association Scholarship
- 2021 Travel award from USNC for ICA with NSF funding to attend the ICC2021
- 2021 Pioneers Student Research Fund, Geospatial Information Sciences Program, UTD
- 2021 PhD Research Small Grants Awarded by the Office of Graduate Education, UTD
- 2021 First Place in GIS Day 2021 Awarded by Geospatial Information Sciences Program, UTD
- 2019 First Place in GIS Day 2019 Awarded by Geospatial Information Sciences Program, UTD
- 2019 Pioneers Student Research Fund, Geospatial Information Sciences Program, UTD
- 2019 First Place in GIS Day 2019 Awarded by the Geography Department at Binghamton University
- 2015 Outstanding Prize in GeoDesign at Esri GIS Software Development Contest

### **PRESENTATIONS**

- 2023 Identify geographical environments influencing emergency response performance. SWAAG,
- 2023 Modeling of emergency incident with GPS trajectory data using random forest algorithm. ICC, August
- 2023 Assessing the role of geographical context in modeling the likelihood of emergency response. AAG, April
- 2022 Driving pattern analysis for emergency vehicle (EV). AutoCarto, November
- 2022 Understanding emergency vehicle movement from GPS trajectory data. GIS Day in UTD, November
- 2022 Understanding 911 Response Time from GPS trajectory data. UTD Research Day, October
- 2022 Driving pattern analysis for emergency vehicle (EV) using multi-source data. UCGIS, Syracuse, NY, June
- 2022 Why is there a delay in a 911 vehicle arriving? The Three Minute Thesis (3MT) Competition, UTD, April
- 2022 Location analytics of routine occurrences (LARO) to identify locations with regularly occurring events. CO, April
- 2022 Location Analytics of Routine Occurrences (LARO) with a case study on traffic accidents. AAG, New York, February
- 2021 location analytics of routine occurrences (LARO) with a case study on traffic accidents. ICC, Italy, December
- **2021** Emergency vehicle data map-matching utilizing the Dijkstra's Algorithm. *GIS Day in UTD*, November
- 2021 Spatial-temporal analysis of traffic accidents for increasing sustainable transportation. The Center for Spatial Studies at UCSB
- 2021 The Three Minute Thesis (3MT) Competition. The University of Texas at Dallas, April
- 2020 Research Showcase Poster Competition, EPPS. The University of Texas at Dallas, October
- 2019 Visualizing (Wild) Fires in Sentinel-2 imagery using custom script in EO Browser. GIS Day in UTD, November
- 2019 Developing an hourly risk model for street networks in Dallas. SWAAG, Fort Worth, Texas. October
- 2019 Integration of Earth observations and in situ data for analyzing lake level changes. GIS Day at Binghamton University, March
- 2019 Integration of Earth observations and in situ data for analyzing lake level changes. AAG, Washington D.C. April

## **ACADEMIC SERVICE**

- 2022 Student judge for Faculty Three Minutes Thesis (3MT) Competition in UTD
- 2022 USGIF Student Assistant Program at the 2022 GEOINT Symposium

# PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

American Association of Geographers

Cartography and Geographic Information Society